Okay
בוקר טוב. boker tov. Alright, today's דף daf is hopefully it's officially
צדיק ז'. tzadik zayin. We are picking up
towards the bottom of the גמרא Gemara in צדיק ו' עמוד א',
tzadik vav amud aleph, so let's see how close we can get
to getting to what today's דף daf actually officially is. The issue
in the משנה Mishna is the is what happens in terms of
the slaves of a woman who is married to a
כהן. kohen. There are two types: the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, the
slaves that she that she retains title to, which are totally hers
except he gets the right of usage, and the slaves that he
owns, the נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. And the משנה Mishna
deals with the ones that she owns, those are the more interesting
ones, and if she's an אלמנה almanah or a גרושה grusha חלוצה
chalutzah אלמנה almanah to a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, she becomes a
חללה chalalah in the mid- so then the point is she can't
eat תרומה terumah because of her being married to him. What about
her slaves? Are they eating through her and then they cannot eat
תרומה? terumah? That's what the משנה Mishna says. The משנה Mishna says
they cannot eat תרומה terumah or maybe we should say essentially no,
this is all back connected to the כהן kohen and therefore the
slaves can. So the משנה Mishna says that they cannot and the
גמרא Gemara says that the reason is is because
קנינו שקנה קנין, kinyano shekanah kinyan, that is the phrase referring to
the wife as a קנין, kinyan, something that is obviously challenging that
we'll have to deal with when we get to מסכת קידושין. masechet
kiddushin. And therefore this is his קנין, kinyan, his wife that owns
something, these slaves, and they eat תרומה. terumah. And why? So that
sounds like it's about him, and the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, but
if she can't eat, if she's not אוכל, ochel, she's not מאכיל,
machil, ultimately they're eating through her. And now the גמרא's Gemara questioning
whether that is actually the principle. Do the are they entitled through
her or does it connect back to him? So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: והרי ממזר שאין אוכל. v'harei mamzer she-ein ochel.
The line starts with the words שאין אוכל. she-ein ochel. The word
ממזר mamzer is the last word of the line right here in
the תוספות Tosafot that starts with the word אלא. Ella. והרי ממזר
שאין אוכל ומאכיל. v'harei mamzer she-ein ochel umachil. How about a ממזר
mamzer who can't eat but he can allow his mother to eat?
What's the case here? The case here is not really about a
ממזר; mamzer; it's ממזר mamzer just to make this more drastic. But
the case here is is that you've got basically a כהן kohen
who is married to a woman, okay, and they have a daughter,
okay, and this daughter let's even do it in a is married
to a ממזר. mamzer. Now really it doesn't have to be a
ממזר. mamzer. It could just be a ישראל, Yisrael, okay, but it's
an extreme example. And they have a and they have a child,
right? Now, is this child a
כהן?
kohen?
No, right?
Because his mother was the daughter of a כהן kohen but his
father's a ישראל Yisrael or even a ממזר mamzer if the case
would be a ממזר. mamzer. He's not a כהן. kohen. Can his
mother now let's say the כהן kohen dies or they get divorced
or
whatever let's say the כהן kohen dies, okay,
can the mother eat תרומה? terumah? Does anybody know the הלכה halacha
that if a woman is married to a כהן kohen and the
כהן kohen dies, whether the woman can continue eating תרומה? terumah?
She didn't get her גט get yet so then...
No, no, no גט. get. The כהן kohen dies.
No, she still gets her כתובה. ketubah.
Forget the כתובה. ketubah. Can a woman who is married to a
כהן kohen and the כהן kohen dies continue eating תרומה? terumah? Unless
she has a child, not a son, a child from the כהן,
kohen, then she's still connected to the כהן kohen family, and then
she can eat תרומה. terumah. Now the הלכה halacha is even if
it's a grandchild, okay? So in this case, the כהן kohen dies,
let's say her daughter dies, she can still eat תרומה terumah because
she has a grandchild that is ultimately ultimately from the כהן kohen
family, even though it comes through a daughter and therefore the child
is not a is not a כהן, kohen, the child could even
be a ממזר, mamzer, okay, but because she's got a grandchild that
came through her marriage to the כהן, kohen, she can still eat
תרומה. terumah. For forever as long as the child's alive? Yep. Forever
as long as the child's alive.
Even though the daughter and child...
even though the child... now the daughter until she was married whatever
could... so that's why it's even more radical to hear because you
know this grandchild would never be able to eat תרומה, terumah, right?
The daughter could before she got married, okay, but this grandchild would
never be able to eat תרומה terumah and nevertheless her grandmother can
eat on her behalf.
Even after she got her כתובה ketubah paid?
Yep. So okay, so thank you. So okay, so therefore we say,
so you see that somebody can have somebody eat on their behalf
even if they themselves cannot eat. So the גמרא Gemara says, start...
all those were in the words והרי ממזר שאין אוכל. v'harei mamzer
she-ein ochel.
So this grandchild doesn't eat, even a ממזר, mamzer, and could make
her grandmother eat. אמר רבינא Amar Ravina קנין דאכיל מאכיל. kinyan d'achil
machil.
No, no, no, obviously there are cases where a descendant can
eat and the and the grandmother will or the mother will, okay?
That's because that's based on the idea that because it's a child
or descendant it back ultimately connects her to the family of the
כהן. kohen. That's a different category. We're not... We're talking about children
or grandchildren. We're talking about the קנין kinyan case, the slave of
the slave or the slave of the wife, again calling a wife
a קנין. kinyan. That's the context. This is a different story. This
is eating by virtue of a child or a grandchild. That's not
relevant. We're talking about eating by virtue of being owned. Okay, and
that's our issue. קנין אוכל kinyan ochel we're talking about. Okay, קאמר,
kamar, קנין אוכל מאכיל. kinyan ochel maachil. Only a קנין kinyan that
eats can feed. Okay, קנין שאינו אוכל אינו מאכיל. kinyan she'aino ochel
eino maachil.
So back to the principle that again calling the wife a קנין
kinyan and if she can't eat, then she can't have her slaves
eat, because ultimately they're eating through her. That's explanation number one of
the משנה. mishna. Now we get to explanation number two. ורבא אמר,
veRava amar, מדאורייתא מיכלא אכלי. mide'raisa michla achli. You know what? You're
right. The slaves of the wife really could eat because indirectly they're
connected to the כהן kohen and forget the fact that the wife
can't eat, in principle they can. מדאורייתא מיכלא אכלי. mide'raisa michla achli.
ורבנן הוא דגזרו בהו. verabbanan hu degazru behu. The rabbis didn't let
the slaves eat in this case, כדי שתאמר, kedei shetomar, and this
was, they did this as an incentive to try to get them
divorced because you know the כהן kohen is married to a גרושה,
grusha, חלוצה, chalutza, or כהן גדול kohen gadol to an אלמנה, almanah,
we don't like that situation. So we want to try to create
certain pressures in order to get them divorced. And here's what we're
going to say. She'll say, look, אני איני אוכלת. ani eini ocheles.
Here it is, my כהן kohen has all this תרומה, truma, a
major source of his income let's say. I can't eat from it,
I'm a חללה. chalala. עבדיי אינם אוכלים. avdai einam ochlim. My slaves
can't eat, I can't even pass down that תרומה truma to my
slaves. Okay? So therefore זונה היא אצלו. zona hi etzlo. I'm basically
like a prostitute to him. Okay? I'm not even really married to
him. I don't get תרומה, truma, my slaves don't get תרומה. truma.
And therefore, זונה היא אצלו. zona hi etzlo. Where am I? ואתי
לאפוקה, va'asi lafuka, and maybe therefore he'll divorce her. That'll cause that
sense of discontent and that'll lead to divorce. So רבא Rava says
in principle you're right, the slaves could eat because they're not even
through her, they're eating because they're connected to him, but it's a
way of our disapproval of the whole situation. Okay, that's רבא's Rava
answer. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, גזירה, gezeira, so רב אשי
Rav Ashi agrees in principle the slaves could eat, but here's the
reason why not. גזירה שמא תאכיל אחר מיתה. gezeira shema ta'achil achar
misa.
We're afraid that she will feed her slaves this תרומה truma even
after the כהן kohen dies. She's only eating by virtue of the
כהן, kohen, maybe if they let her feed the תרומה truma now,
she'll continue to feed them after the כהן kohen dies. Of course
the גמרא gemara says that should be a concern all the time.
So the גמרא gemara says, אלא מעתה ela mei'ata בת ישראל שניסת
לכהן, bas yisrael shenises lekohen, the classic case of a Jewish woman
married to a כהן. kohen. לא תאכיל, lo sa'achil, let her not
feed her slaves תרומה. truma. גזירה שמא תאכיל אחר מיתה, gezeira shema
ta'achil achar misa, maybe she'll continue to feed them after that. אלא
אמר רב אשי, ela amar Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi
says fine, forget that. באלמנה לכהן גדול. be'almana lekohen gadol. Here's the
reason why we don't allow this case, because there's one case we
do have to be concerned about that will lead to a problem.
What's the case? That the woman who's married to the כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, the אלמנה, almanah, okay, she actually is also a בת
כהן. bas kohen. Now if she's a בת כהן, bas kohen, she
will say the following. דאתיא למירויי, de'asya leru'ei, she'll come to sort
of פסקן pasken for herself. And here's what she'll come to reason.
מעיקרא אכלי בתרומה דבי נשא. me'ikara achli bitruma devei nasha.
Originally
these slaves were eating תרומה truma because of through my father's, you
know, through דבי נשא debei nasha is, you know, the
woman's house, but meaning, you know, the house that I came from,
you know, actually it means the father's house, but not my husband,
not who I'm married to. So I was eating תרומה, truma, they
were eating תרומה truma by virtue of the fact that I was
a בת כהן. bas kohen. Where
were we? Or actually no she's- yeah. Okay, sorry. דבי נשא. debei
nasha. Oh where am I? באלמנה לכהן גדול דאתיא למירויי מעיקרא אכלי
בתרומה דבי נשא. be'almana lekohen gadol de'asya leru'ei me'ikara achli bitruma devei
nasha.
Hold on let me just check רש״י Rashi one second.
Yeah.
Okay, originally they ate תרומה truma when I was, you know, in
my father's house. Okay, these slaves, because they were eating by virtue
of the fact that I was a בת כהן. bas kohen. אינסיבא
להאי, inseiva lehaya,
I married this כהן, kohen, אכלי בתרומה דגברא. achli bitruma degavra. They
continued to eat תרומה truma by virtue of my husband. דהשתא הדרא
לה מילתא כמעיקרא. dehashta hadra lei milsa kemaise. Now that my husband
has died, they'll go back to their original state and they'll continue
to eat תרומה. truma. ולא ידעה, velo yada, she's not aware דמעיקרא
לא שויתיה לנפשה חללה. de'me'ikara lo shavisi lenafsha chalala.
Before when they were eating when before she got married to this
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, then the slaves were eating because she wasn't
yet a חללה. chalala. השתא שויתיה לנפשה חללה. hashta shavisi nafsha chalala.
Now she's become a חללה, chalala, so they can't eat. Okay, so
basically what he's saying is it's complicated, but basically you're right in
principle these slaves can eat because they're connected to the כהן, kohen,
but we're afraid she'll continue to have them eat after she gets
divorced. After the כהן kohen dies. Isn't that a concern all the
time? No, here there'll be a particular logic she'll think. She'll think
look, my slaves were eating before I married the כהן kohen because
I'm a
בת כהן. bas kohen. But she won't be aware that in the
process she became a חללה Chalala and that because she's an אלמנה
Almanah married to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and that makes her
into a חללה Chalala when they have sex with a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, that's the whole assumption of the משנה. Mishna. The problem
of the משנה, Mishna, the reason she becomes disqualified is because it's
a forbidden marriage between a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and an אלמנה
Almanah or a כהן Kohen and a גרושה Grusha and that makes
her into a חללה, Chalala, that's the whole, that's the major principle
of what makes this case an interesting case is that she's the
חללה. Chalala. So because in the process she became a חללה, Chalala,
even after the כהן Kohen dies, she does not go back to
having her slaves eat because then as a חללה Chalala her slaves
can no longer eat. Yes.
The word כהנת Kohenet means the daughter of a כהן?
Kohen? Yes.
Okay. Yeah. So she became a חללה, Chalala, basically.
So in the case on the right, you know where that in
the black? Right? So they don't marry... right, no, which is a
regular person. So she is forbidden. In contrast to this case, because
she's also, she can't have her slaves eat, this woman would be
able to even have her slaves eat if she had a kid,
right?
Yes. Okay. Yeah. Alright. Yes, Joe, you had a question?
I just want to clarify: she was already an אלמנה Almanah when
she married the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. She didn't become an אלמנה
Almanah by virtue of his...
No, but she became a חללה Chalala because she was an אלמנה
Almanah who had sex with a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. There's a... Okay. What about the גרושה Grusha of a
כהן Kohen himself? She herself?
She can eat as long as there's a child.
Right. Okay, but not here because she's a חללה. Chalala. Okay.
Alright, חברה, Chevra, moving on. So it's another reason, complicated reason why
in principle these slaves could eat but because it'll lead to a
problem where she'll continue to feed them where she won't be allowed
to. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תינח אלמנה כהנת,
Teinech Almanah Kohenet,
so that makes sense in the case of an אלמנה כהנת. Almanah
Kohenet. אבל אלמנה בת ישראל מאי איכא למימר? Aval Almanah Bat Yisrael
ma ika le-meimar?
Why does this משנה Mishna apply even to a case of a
non-כהנת? Kohenet? So the גמרא Gemara says: באלמנותא לא פליגי רבנן. Be-almanuta
lo pligi rabanan. Oh, לא פלוג. Lo plug.
So since it's one case they're concerned about, that she might say
we go back to square one and so on, therefore they say
in all these cases the slaves can't eat. Okay, so basically we
have two answers. One is that the slaves only eat by virtue
of her, which is the simple answer and she's a חללה Chalala
they can't eat. The other is that they eat by virtue of
him and there's special reasons that we have to make a גזירה
Gezeirah here. Moving on. אתמר. Itmar. המכניסת שום לבעלה. Ha-machneset shum le-ba'alah.
A woman who brings in garlic to her husband. No, I'm teasing.
A woman... שום Shum means that you evaluate the property
and שמין Shamin means like to assess the property, that's the word,
you assess the property. Okay. And that's what we refer to as
the נכסי צאן ברזל. Nichsei Tzon Barzel. That's when the כתובה Kethubah
says, you know, בין בתכשיטי בין בזהב בין בכסף הכל קיבל עליו
החתן במאה זקוקים כסף צור, Bein be-takhshiti bein be-zahav bein be-khesef ha-kol
kibel alav ha-chatan be-me'ah zekukim kesef tzor, which means: here's all the
property she's bringing in, we're assessing their value to be a hundred,
you know, coins of silver. And therefore when they get divorced, or
if he dies first, she's able to take out of the marriage,
out of the husband's estate, these hundred, you know, hundred silver coins
because of whatever the זקוקים Zekukim is. Anyway, ten thousand dollars.
Now, so that means you assess their value and that's the amount
the husband owns. That's נכסי צאן ברזל. Nichsei Tzon Barzel. Title transfers
to the husband. נכסי מלוג Nichsei Milug she retains title, right, he
just gets use. Here title transfers, and title is transferring and then
he's going to be the one that's going to benefit from the
increase but also suffer any loss. So what she gets is the
dollar value, she's assured the dollar value. And that's why you do
a שומא, Shuma, you do an assessment of how much it's worth.
Okay. So המכניסת שום לבעלה, Ha-machneset shum le-ba'alah, she brings in money
into the marriage, it's נכסי צאן ברזל, Nichsei Tzon Barzel, you do
an assessment, you determine how much it's worth. Now, this is the
question that I think Michael or somebody asked me the other day.
Let's say the husband dies and the stuff is still around, the
field is still around, the car, the slaves, whatever it is, is
still around. She wants to take the stuff back. She doesn't just
want the dollar value. So what's the story? היא אומרת כלי אני
נוטלת, Hi omeret keli ani notelat, I'm taking back my vessels. והוא
אומר Ve-hu omer so we're dealing in a case of divorce והוא
אומר דמים אני נותן. Ve-hu omer damim ani noten. No, I'm only
paying you for them. Like, I totally took possession, 100% mine, and
I just owe you money. So that's the question. Is it fundamentally
that she still has a right to reclaim them? Or it's just
that any benefit he'll keep, any loss he'll have to suffer, but
fundamentally they began as hers and she has a right to reclaim
them? Or it's fundamentally he just owes her money? So הדין עם
מי? Ha-din im mi? Who's, who's right? Who has law on their
side? רב יהודה אמר, Rav Yehuda amar, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said:
הדין עמה. Ha-din imah.
She's got the law on her side. She's able to claim back
her vessels. ורב אמי אמר הדין עמו. Ve-Rav Ami amar ha-din imo.
The law is with him. רב יהודה אמר הדין עמה משום שבח
בית אביה
היא. Rav Yehuda amar ha-din imah mishum shevach beit aviha hi. It's
because it's the benefit of the father's house, the increase of the
father's house. Meaning, this is the stuff that she got for dowry
from her father's house. And therefore she's entitled to it, which is
a pretty funny argument. It's not... It's not like a legal point,
it's just somehow saying, she should be entitled to it! This is
what she got from her father's house, she should be entitled to
reclaim it. רב אמי אמר הדין עמו Rav Ami amar hadin imo
כי בא אפוטרופא ki va apotropa that he's entitled to it. כיון
דאמר מר kivan d'amar mar since we say אם מתו מתו לו
ואם הותירו הותירו לו, im mesu mesu lo v'im hosiru hosiru lo,
if they die, right, that's in the Mishnah, that describes the consequence
of נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. If they die, it's his
loss, if they increase, it's his gain. So what does that show
you? So now here, not in my Gemara, but most of these
Gemaras have actually a that they're all
in all the manuscripts, there was, yeah, here it is. In all
the manuscripts there's actually a line that's a line that's not in
our Gemara and you can see how it got left out because
it's considered השמטה על ידי הדומות hashmata al yedei hadomos when the
סופר sofer jumps from one line to the next because it's the
same word. So here's actually how the sentence ends. It says, so
since it says if they die, it's his loss and if they
increase, it's his increase, so ברשותיה קיימי, birshusei kaimei, so clearly it
shows that it's now in his possession וכדידיה דמו uch'didiah damu and
it's like it's fully his. And that's the proof, right? That's pretty
reasonable. If it increases it's his, if it decreases he lost, it
shows it's his proof. So then the Gemara now says תנן, t'nan,
let's look at our Mishnah. ואלו הן נכסי צאן ברזל אם מתו
מתו לו ואם הותירו הותירו לו. V'eilu hein nichsei tzon barzel im
mesu mesu lo v'im hosiru hosiru lo. So it goes back and
it quotes the same law. Okay, so basically he says since if
it increases or decreases it's all his, obviously that shows that it's
come to his possession. Now let's take a look at what we
can prove from the Mishnah. Okay, so it says והואיל וחייב באחריותן
יאכלו. v'hoil v'chayav b'achrayusan yochalu. So it says, and that seems to
be a proof. It says he's obligated in
their, he's responsible for them, and therefore they eat. So that seems
to prove two things. Number one, it says he's responsible for them.
That seems to signal that they're his. And number two, if they
can eat, if these slaves that he got as נכסי צאן ברזל
nichsei tzon barzel from the dowry can eat, even though his wife
is a חללה, chalala, that shows that they're considered to be his
slaves, right? So the simple sense of the Mishnah clearly is that
these are his slaves and that's why they're entitled to eat. So
doesn't that prove that she cannot retrieve them if there's a divorce?
So אמר רב ספרא, amar Rav Safra, so Rav Safra says back,
no. מי קתני דהן שלו? mi katani d'hein shelo? It doesn't say
the slaves are his. Look, the language is very specific. It says
הואיל וחייב באחריותן קתני. hoil v'chayav b'achrayusan katani. It says that he's
responsible for them. So it's a legal sort of relationship to them
where yes, he benefits from any increase, he suffers any loss, but
that doesn't have to mean that they're considered his, right? That could
just be the condition of the, you know, the nature of the
sort of legal rights that he has and responsibilities he has without
absolutely claiming that they're his. The language is חייב באחריותו, chayav b'achrayuso,
the language is not that they're his. ולעולם לאו דידיה נינהו, ul'olam
lav didei ninhu, they're not his. Okay, but now you have an
interesting situation that they're not his but they still eat Terumah by
virtue of this relationship, right? So now we get always into this
interesting gray zone, right? Is it possible that they're eating Terumah because
of he is so much sort of has so many rights regarding
them that they're eat and responsibility that they're eating Terumah because it's
as if they're his, but still being able to technically say they're
still not his, they're still hers, and she can still retrieve them.
So let's take a look. That's the debate. So the Gemara says
like
this. וכל היכא דחייב באחריותן אכלי בתרומה? v'chol heicha d'chayav b'achrayusan achli
b'seruma? So that's what the Gemara's going to question. So are you
really going to tell me that being responsible
for their loss is enough of a relationship to entitle them to
eat Terumah even if they're not his? Let's test that theory because
now you're saying you don't have to own them and they can
still eat
Terumah. והתנן, v'hatnan, we taught in the Mishnah, ישראל ששכר פרה מכהן,
Yisrael she'sachar para mi'kohen, a
Yisrael rented a cow from a Kohen. Now when you rent a
cow, you're liable for loss and theft. That's a type of a
חייב באחריות, chayav b'achrayus, you're liable for any loss. So הרי זה
יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה. harei zeh yachilena karshinei seruma. Since they're still owned
by a Kohen, they're considered the Kohen's and he can feed the
cow this like animal fodder of Terumah. In the reverse, כהן ששכר
פרה מישראל, Kohen she'sachar para mi'Yisrael, if a Kohen rented a cow
from
a Yisrael, אף על פי שמזונותיה עליו, af al pi she'mezonoseiha alav,
even though he is responsible to feed the cow, he'll be responsible
for any loss, nevertheless, even though he's got all this responsibility and
חייב באחריות, chayav b'achrayus, it's still the Yisrael's cow. And the הלכה
halacha is לא יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה, lo yachilena karshinei seruma, he can't
feed it Terumah. So you see, being חייב באחריות chayav b'achrayus is
not enough to allow
something you don't own to eat Terumah. So if the slaves are
eating Terumah, it must be more than he's just responsible for them,
it must be a real sense of ownership. So the Gemara says,
one minute. There are different degrees of what it means to be
responsible for something. It's a sliding scale. Renting is a low level
of responsibility. The relationship he has to the slaves is a high
level of responsibility. That makes things different. So the Gemara says one
minute, ותסברא, v'sisbara, does that make sense that that's a proof against
this idea? נהי נמי דחייב בגניבה ואבידה, Nihi nami dechayev bigneva va'aveida,
when you rent it's true you're liable for theft and loss, but
for אונס, ones, but here's a whole list of things you're not
liable for. Number two, if some accident happens to us, right? the
stray it you know something's out of your control. Number two, בתיכשא.
betichsha. Let's say it got thinner. You rent a cow and it
got thinner, you know, just naturally. You don't have to somehow make
up the difference unless you're actually negligent, right? Or you know or
somehow got weaker. Or בנפחת קמיא. benifchat kamaya. Let's say the market
changed. You rented a cow was worth a thousand dollars. You returned
it it was worth nine hundred because the market changed. Gotta give
the guy a hundred dollars? Of course not, right? So therefore your
responsibility as a renter is very limited for theft and loss, whereas
when you take the slaves in in the marriage, let's say the
market changes. You took the slaves in and the slaves were worth
a thousand dollars. And now you're getting divorced and the slaves are
worth five hundred. They didn't get any worse, just the market changed.
You have to give your wife an extra five hundred dollars.
What about the original slave?
And even if you give the original slave, you'd have to make
up the difference. So it doubles after? Yeah yeah yeah, you have
to pay for all that, which is a proof that it's not
just some liability, it's really a sense of ownership because you always
have to pay back the full value. So it's nothing like normal
liability and therefore and therefore says the גמרא, Gemara, we don't have
to call it ownership. You're right, it's starting to sound a lot
like ownership. You've taken these slaves, you get divorced a day later
and now because the market has changed they're worth less and you
have to pay back more, you have to give them back plus
a hundred dollars. Okay, so it doesn't sound like normal liability. It
sounds like ownership with a debt. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
maybe not. We're going to insist that there's this middle zone that's
called she's still owns it but you have complete liability and also
you get any increase in value. So you have all the consequences
of ownership, but we're not going to call it ownership. Okay, yes.
Is it something one put instead of in the term that and
in unless the owner came with the cow when you rented it?
Yeah. No that's when you borrow it, not when you rent it.
Oh okay.
Yeah. And the other thing is just this the value that she
gets back, is it the value at the end of the period
or the value when it was originally?
No, the value when he took it in when it was originally
assessed. It is.
Yeah. But what if it increased in value?
Then he gets to keep the difference. So that that's the point.
The point is that this looks like ownership because all of the
issues right well right it's like you know so any she gives
the money. She's entitled to get the full value back but also
any increase he keeps any increase, he makes up any difference. It
doesn't matter if he's at fault, not at fault, it's because market
changed, whatever the reason is. So that looks a lot like he
took over title and she just is owed money. But the גמרא
Gemara is saying maybe we can insist no. Maybe we can insist
that she retains title but he has a very unique set of
rights and responsibilities to this property that she has title to. Number
one is he's entitled to any increase in value. Number two is
he's obligated to pay up any loss in value, no matter how
much it's his fault or not his fault or how much it's
about market changes, but maybe technically she still owns it. And therefore
this degree of חייב באחריותו, chayev beachrayuso, the slaves would eat תרומה.
terumah. Okay, so that's the argument. We all agree that it looks
a lot like ownership, but is it really ownership? But we're saying
it might be that it's not ownership, but because it's this amount
of rights and responsibilities, therefore it's close enough that the slaves can
eat תרומה. terumah. All right. Yep. Some of these slaves have children.
Who gets them? She does or he does?
He does.
Yeah. All right, so now גמרא Gemara would say like this. Okay,
הלא דמיא אלא סיפא. halo damya ela seifa. So if you if
you want to compare it to a case, it's compared to a
of a high level of rights and responsibilities. It's comparable to the
end of this ברייתא. braita. Which is what? הלא דמיא halo damya
where am I?
אלא סיפא. ela seifa. ישראל ששם פרה מכהן, Yisro shesham para mikohen,
if a ישראל Yisro basically assesses the cost of a cow from
a כהן kohen and he takes it and he says I will
give you back its full value, then לא יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה. lo
yachilena karshinei terumah. He can't feed the תרומה terumah because then it
becomes like his, even though it doesn't say he he took title.
He just assesses the value and promises to restore it in full
value
regardless of fault or anything. אבל כהן ששם פרה מישראל, aval kohen
shesham para miYisro, but if a כהן kohen assesses the cow from
a ישראל Yisro and promises to return it in full value regardless
of market or any other changes, then יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה. yachilena karshinei
terumah. He can feed it, even though that's not actually taking title.
So of course you could say no maybe you could argue back
and say no that is taking title. But this is the question:
this unique relationship that he has to restore it in full value
and he gets any benefit and any increase, do we say okay
effectively that's ownership or do we say no, it exists in some
space where she still owns it but he has all those rights?
Okay, but maybe that's enough that they'll eat תרומה, terumah, but technically
therefore she's still entitled to demand taking it back. Okay, so let's
take a look. יתיב רבה ורב יוסף, yasiv Rabbah verav Yosef, so
רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף Rav Yosef were sitting בשלהי פירקיה דרב
נחמן, beshilei pirkei deRav Nachman, at the end of the דרשא drasha
of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So רב... Rav... Rav Nachman finished his
דרשה drasha and they were hanging back and talking in תורה. Torah.
ויתבי וקאמרי V'yativ v'ka'amri and they were sitting and saying תניא כוותיה
דרב יהודה ותניא כוותיה דרבי אמי Tanya kevataih d'Rav Yehuda v'tanya kevataih
d'Rabbi Ami we taught like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that she's entitled
to it and we taught like רבי אמי Rabbi Ami that he's
entitled to it. תניא כוותיה דרבי אמי Tanya kevataih d'Rabbi Ami we
taught like רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. עבדי צאן ברזל יוצאין בשן ועין
לאיש אבל לא לאשה Avdi tzon barzel yotzin b'shen v'ayin la'ish aval
lo l'isha
let's say these slaves that he took in as the dowry and
they're צאן ברזל, tzon barzel, he owes their value.
He knocks out their eye or tooth, then they would go out
because he's considered their master and they go out for free. But
if she knocks out an eye or tooth they don't go out
because he's not considered their master. So that sounds like he's the
one that has full title. Okay, now that's the prima facie like
רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. תניא כוותיה דרב יהודה Tanya kevataih d'Rav Yehuda
we taught like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. המכנסת שום לבעלה Hamachneses shum
l'ba'ala
so if she brings in this
assessed-valued property to her husband, אם רצה בעל למכור לא ימכור im
ratza ba'al limkor lo yimkor he's not allowed to sell it. Right,
now the fact that he's not allowed to sell it, why wouldn't
he be allowed to sell it? According to the idea that it's
his he could totally sell it, he just has a debt to
her, they're 100% his. So the fact that he's not allowed shows
that she's still entitled to take it back and that she still
has rights to it. מכרו שניהם לפרנסה Machru shneihem l'parnasa now
if either of them sold it because they needed I don't know,
you know, to put food on the table, רש"י Rashi just says
that's just a standard example. Did I skip a line?
ולא עוד אלא אפילו הכניס
לה
שום משלה
V'lo od ela afilu
hichnis
lah shum mishela
even if he basically contributed to her dowry, which is an interesting
idea. He said look here take this lovely you know I don't
know my grandmother's china, that'll be part of your dowry and I'll
pay so essentially he's contributing to her dowry and then she's going
to take it out of the marriage or at least their value.
Even in that case, אם רצה בעל למכור לא ימכור im ratza
ba'al limkor lo yimkor he can't sell it because, which again shows
that he doesn't really have full title. Some degree she still has
rights. מכרו שניהם לפרנסה Machru shneihem l'parnasa if they both or if
either of them as way רש"י Rashi sells it because they had
to put food on the table, רש"י Rashi says it doesn't have
to be that reason but that would just be otherwise you normally
wouldn't sell. זה היה מעשה לפני רבן גמליאל Ze haya ma'aseh lifnei
Rabban Gamliel this came before רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. ואמר הבעל מוציא
מיד הלקוחות V'amar haba'al motzi miyad halokchos that the sale is completely
void and the husband retrieves it from the people he sold it
to because he has no rights to sell the property that the
wife brought in. Okay so this seems like a very good proof.
If he really has full title and it's just a debt, why
would he not have rights to sell this property? Okay so that
really seems like quite a good proof.
Property that he literally brought in?
Well yes, but property that he contributed. Contributed, right. Right. Okay. אמר
רבא אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרב יהודה Amar Rava Amar Rav Nachman
Halacha k'Rav Yehuda so that last ברייתא Braita was pretty persuasive. So
now רבא Rava is saying we rule like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda.
She is entitled to retrieve the property that she brought in. Again,
if it's worth more, here's an interesting question. If it's worth less
he makes up the difference. If it's worth more what does she
do? So if she brought in like I don't know twelve place
settings of china and now they've doubled in value, does she take
out six or does she take out twelve and pay back the
difference? If she brought in a vintage I don't know you know
Mustang, whatever and now it's doubled in value you don't take away
half a car. So what do you do? Do you take the
whole car and pay the difference? Right that's not exactly clear how
that will play out. The גמרא Gemara will do like one or
two scenarios. But anyway in principle she is entitled to take it
back out. How that plays out in the fact that it's limited
to their original value that's not exactly clear. Let's take a look.
We rule like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן
Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nachman so רבא Rava said to רב נחמן
Rav Nachman because he said רב נחמן Rav Nachman was the one
who said we rule like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and רבא Rava
is passing on that tradition. So רבא Rava now said to רב
נחמן Rav Nachman והתניא כוותיה דרבי אמי V'tanya kevataih d'Rabbi Ami
we just taught a ברייתא Braita like רבי אמי? Rabbi Ami? The
ברייתא Braita about the what do you call it, about the שן
ועין shen v'ayin which was not so persuasive as תוספות Tosfos says.
Even if they're hers because he has all those rights it could
still be that the same way they eat תרומה terumah by virtue
of him the idea of going free by the שן ועין shen
v'ayin could be by virtue of him. So תוספות Tosfos doesn't understand
why that was a proof to רבי אמי Rabbi Ami but that's
what רבא Rava said. That whole story about the going out by
the eye and the tooth, that seems to be a proof to
רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. התניא כוותיה דרבי אמי Ha tanya kevataih d'Rabbi
Ami so the גמרא Gemara says אף על גב דתניא כוותיה דרבי
אמי Af al gav d'tanya kevataih d'Rabbi Ami you know what, even
though the ברייתא Braita seems to go like him מסתברא טעמא דרב
יהודה משום שבח בית אביה. mistavra ta'ama d'Rav Yehuda mishum shevach beis
aviha. It makes sense like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda because ultimately this
is stuff she got from her father's house, which is again quite
fascinating, right? That's not really much of a legal argument. Okay she
got it from her father's house fine, but what happens once she
brings it in? You know and there's a textual evidence but we're
like discarding it because there's a sense like she should be entitled
to it. All right anyway but actually to me the stronger ברייתא
Braita was like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was that it is hers
because that's all about his not being allowed to sell it. Okay
now a story. ההיא איתתא דאעילה ליה לגברא אצטלא דמילתא Hahi it-tetha
d'ayeila lei l'gavrei itztela d'mileisa
there's a woman that brought in with her dowry a very like
a cloak of fine wool בכתובתה b'ksubasa for her dowry. שכי shachi
then the husband and died. Okay, so now based on what we
said, if we rule like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, she should be
able to take it back out. But שקלוה יתמי *shakluy yasmi*, before
she had a chance to do anything, the orphans came ופרסוה אמיתנא
*upharsua amisna* and they spread it over the dead body and they
wanted to use it as a shroud. And we know that something
that is assigned as a shroud and used as a shroud for
dead body is אסור assur בהנאה *asur bahana'ah*. So אמר רבא *Amar
Rava* קנייה מתנא *kanye misna*, the dead body acquires it, meaning it's
now considered a shroud and she loses her rights, or I mean
she's still entitled to her value from the estate for her for
her dowry, but she but yes but she loses any rights in
this particular object. So אמר לה ננחי בריה דרב יוסף בריה דרבא
לרב כהנא *Amar lei Nemchi brei deRav Yosef brei deRava leRav Kahana*,
so this Nemchi the grandson of Rava said to רב כהנא *Rav
Kahana*, והאמר רבא אמר רב נחמן הלכה halacha כרבי יהודה *Veha'amar Rava
amar Rav Nachman halacha keRabbi Yehuda*, don't we rule like רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*? And therefore it should have been hers. And if you
take somebody else's garment and you put it on a dead body,
it doesn't become a shroud, you can't change the status of something
you don't own, you can only do that with your own objects.
So if this is hers, the orphans weren't entitled to use it
as a shroud and it shouldn't change its status. So אמר ליה
*Amar lei* back to him, מי לא מודי רבי יהודה דמחוסר גוביינא
*Mi lo modei Rabbi Yehuda demchusar guvaina*? Even though רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says she's entitled to take it back, it still needs to
be collected. Meaning, so this becomes a fascinating question: is רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* saying it's hers, the title remains hers, or is she
saying she has a right to retrieve it? Technically the title is
his, but she ultimately retains the right to re-exercise
her claim on it if he dies. So it's a little bit
sounding like the latter. Like it's not like it's totally her title.
She has a right to claim it, but it requires to go
ahead and to be claimed and to be collected. And until that
point it's not yet her, or it's not certainly not under her
control. Right? I mean, all along it was under the husband's control.
So even after the husband dies, it doesn't automatically revert to her
control. That needs to actually be delivered and collected. So therefore, דכיון
דמחוסר גוביינא ברשותיה קאי *dekeivan demchusar guvaina birshuseih kai*. And since it
does require being collected, it's still under the control of the husband
or the heirs. Okay? And therefore they're in a position, again, do
they have title, does she have title, it's not exactly spelled out.
It might be she has title but no control. But anyway, since
they're the ones still in control, they are in a position to
use it for the dead body and then that'll take away her
rights. Why? Why? רבא *Rava* well no, he still owes her money,
she still gets the money from the estate, she just loses the
rights in this object.
Because she doesn't have any obligation to bury her husband and provide
תכריכין *tachrichim*.
Yeah, that's a different story. But yes, רבא לטעמיה דאמר רבא *Rava
leta'ameih de'amar Rava*, רבא *Rava* goes according to his reasoning because רבא
*Rava* said הקדש חמץ ושחרור מוציאין מידי שיעבוד *hekdesh chametz veshichrur motzi'in
miyedei shibud*. That if you basically have a lien on a piece
on my estate and I go ahead and I sanctify, you have
a lien on my plot of land and I sanctify it... Okay,
actually no, that would be a קדושת דמים *kedushas damim* example. This
is only קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf*. You have a lien on my
cow and I make it into a קרבן *korban*, but it's only
when you actually change its status, not just you transfer its ownership
to הקדש *hekdesh*. I make the cow into a קרבן *korban*, your
lien disappears. Okay, it's that idea of that I've made it into
a קרבן *korban* changes its identity. You're a non-Jew, you have a
lien on my חמץ *chametz*, it becomes it becomes פסח *Pesach*, חמץ
*chametz* becomes אסור בהנאה *asur bahana'ah*, your lien disappears, that changes its
identity. Okay? You have a lien on my slave, I free my
slave, my slave has now transformed his identity, your lien disappears. So
here too, she has a type of a lien or a right
on this cloak, but they basically put it on the dead body,
they made it אסור בהנאה *asur bahana'ah*, that's like the חמץ הפסח
*chametz haPesach* case, or like that just maybe even more like the
חמץ הפסח *chametz haPesach* case, and that completely therefore transfers its identity
and therefore all of her monetary rights, all of her have gone
basically are removed. So that's why that worked. But the important conceptual
point for us immediately being that even if she is entitled to
it, it doesn't mean it's automatically reverts to her control. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר רב יהודה *Amar
Rav Yehuda*, says רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, top of סז עמוד א
*samech zayin amud aleph*. הכניסה לו שני כלים באלף זוז *Hichnisa lo
shenei keilim be'elef zuz*. So now we're going to get an interesting
case, right, similar to sort of what some of the scenarios I
was giving you. She brings in two vessels worth a thousand dollars,
ושבחו ועמדו על אלפיים *veshavchu ve'amdu al alpayim*, and now they're worth
two thousand dollars. What does she retrieve?
So אחד נוטלת בכתובתה *echad noseles biskusasa*, so one she gets back
because she's entitled to get it back, ואחד נותנת דמים ונוטלתה מפני
שבח בית אביה *ve'echad nosenes damim venoselesah mipnei shevach beis aviha*. And
the other one she actually is entitled to demand the other one
back and she just has to pay the increase in value. So
that's like a scenario I gave you, okay, which is that she
actually is entitled to get it all back and if it's worth
more she pays she pays the difference. Now why? Maybe she should
only really be entitled to one because she's only has rights up
to the value of what she brought in. So again the reason
is מפני שבח בית אביה *mipnei shevach beis aviha*. No, again, a
special consideration that we give her, this is the stuff that she
brought in from her father's house. Again, this is even if technically
she didn't bring it in from her father's house, let's say she
married after she had earned money for herself, but it doesn't matter,
conceptual conceptually, it's stuff she brought in from her father's house. Therefore
we're going to, you know, sort of have the law favor her
in these types of things and give her the right to retrieve
both of them even though now it's worth double and pay the
difference. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashmalan,
what are you teaching me? שבח בית אביה דידה הוי, shevach beit
aviha didah havei, so that she's entitled to what she brought in.
הא אמר רב יהודה חדא זימנא, ha amar rav yehuda chada zimna,
didn't we already say that? No. מהו דתימא הני מילי היכא דמטי
למשקל בכתובתה, mahu detema hani mili heicha demati lemishka biktuvata, maybe that's
only up to the original value of the כתובה, ktuvah, אבל מטעם
דמי למשקל לאו, aval mitam damei lemishka lav, but to actually be
able to pay the difference in value and take stuff that went
beyond the original value in order to retrieve it, maybe she wouldn't
have that right? קא משמע לן kamashmalan that she does. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara is very clear that she has the right to
retrieve everything she brought in. If it's worth more she pays the
difference. And the flip would also be true now, if it's worth
less, she retrieves everything and the husband's estate has to pay the
difference. Okay? So that exactly is all of this is done, you
know, and again it's interesting the way sort of the desire to
give her back what she brought in
drives the way in which we determine her rights in this situation.
What do we actually do today?
What we do today I don't know. You have to first go
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where they handle these cases and there
was a lot of תקנות takanot to protect the woman's interests even
more in the time of the גאונים Geonim and so on. All
right, next משנה. mishnah. בת ישראל שנישאת לכהן ומת והניחה מעוברת. bat
yisrael shenises lekhohein umess vehinichah meuberet.
So that was what happens if as a result of the marriage
she became a חללה, chalalah, what impact that has on her נכסי
מלוג. nechasei milog. Okay, so that was the focus was on נכסי
מלוג, nechasei milog, which is interesting because it's her property although then
we got into an interesting discussion of נכסי צאן ברזל nechasei tzon
barzel and to what degree she retains the title on that as
well. Now, that's as a result of marriage that it was an
אסור marriage and she became a חללה. chalalah. Now we turn to
the question about not the marriage, but a child or a fetus
and the role that the fetus plays in terms of her status
and in terms of the slave status. So let's take a look.
So you had a Jewish woman who, a non-כהנת, kohenet, who is
married to a כהן kohein ומת umess and then the כהן kohein
dies והניחה מעוברת vehinichah meuberet and leaves her pregnant. Now, when a
כהן kohein dies and if again what we said before is, if
he leaves behind a child through this woman, the woman continues to
eat תרומה. terumah. But here he did not leave behind a born
child, he left behind an unborn child, he left behind a pregnant
wife. What's the story?
The גמרא Gemara. doesn't talk about the story with her, I'll just
tell you, the story is she doesn't eat, she doesn't eat until
the child is born. Okay, she doesn't eat by virtue of an
unborn child. But what's the story about the slaves? Okay? So לא
יאכלו עבדיה בתרומה, lo yokhlu avadeha biterumah, the slaves cannot eat תרומה
terumah מפני חלקו של עובר mipnei chelko shel ubar because of the
portion of the עובר. ubar. Now, עבדיה avadeha is a little funny
because the way it really means his slaves. Okay? He's got slaves.
Now, he leaves behind slaves and let's say he leaves behind sons.
So the sons inherit the slaves. So do the slaves continue to
eat תרומה terumah after he dies? Sure, because they're now owned by
the sons and they eat by virtue of the sons. But one
of the part owners of the slaves is this unborn fetus. Okay?
Because assuming that he would be a son, we don't know, but
if he were a son, he would be one of the unborn
owners of the slave, a partial owner of the slave. So because
he has a partial ownership in the slave and he's not yet
born, so he's not yet in a position where he's entitled to
eat תרומה terumah and to have others eat on behalf of him,
none of the slaves can eat תרומה terumah because they are part
ten percent of them is not entitled to eat תרומה. terumah. The
ten percent of them that's owned by the unborn son is not
entitled to eat תרומה terumah and the ninety percent that's owned by
the other let's say nine brothers or whatever is entitled, but that
part of me that's owned by the unborn son, he's not yet
entitled so I cannot eat תרומה terumah by virtue of him but
I'm owned partly by him, so therefore the slaves cannot eat תרומה.
terumah.
Yes, I was going to ask that question. Okay, does it tell
us?
Yes, yes, yes, that's the opinion of this משנה. mishnah. The גמרא
gemara well there's a lot of assumptions there. Okay, so let's take
a look. לא יאכלו עבדיה בתרומה מפני חלקו של עובר lo yokhlu
avadeha biterumah mipnei chelko shel ubar because of the portion of the
עובר. ubar. שהעובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל. sheha'ubar posel ve'eino ma'akhil. The עובר
ubar invalidates and does not feed. So invalidates means he invalidates the
existing slaves from eating, he creates problems, and also he does not
help anybody, he doesn't meaning his mother can't eat by virtue of
him either. Okay? So פוסל ואינו מאכיל. posel ve'eino ma'akhil.
So he's the worst of both worlds,
right?
If he was completely
seen as not existing yet then the slaves would eat. If he
was completely seen as born, his mother would eat. Right now because
he's in a middle state, it's enough that he has a portion
of the slaves but not enough that they can eat and he's
not enough yet of a full person that and his mother can't
eat by virtue of him. דברי רבי יוסי, divrei Rabi Yosi, that's
what רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi says. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
to רבי יוסי, Rabi Yosi, מאחר שהערת לנו על בת ישראל לכהן,
me'achar she'he'arta lanu al bat yisrael lekhohein, if you're going to tell
this is true about a בת ישראל bat yisrael woman married to
a כהן, kohein, אף בת כהן לכהן, af bat kohein lekhohein, the
same logic should be even if she was a daughter of a
כהן kohein married to
a
כהן. kohein. the slaves can't eat on account of the עובר. ubar.
What, why does it matter if the mother is a כהן kohen
or the mother is a בת כהן bat kohen or the mother
is a בת ישראל? bat Yisrael? So אף בת כהן לכהן ומתה
ויש לה עובר במעיה לא יאכלו עבדיה בשביל חלקו של עובר. af
bat kohen le'kohen u'meta v'yesh lah ubar b'me'eha lo yochlu avadeha bishvil
chelko shel ubar.
And we don't know what his response
is, was he agreeing with them?
Well, it's not clear whether they disagree with him or not, but
they're just saying according to your logic there should not be a
difference between whether the mother is a ישראל Yisrael or a כהן.
kohen.
No, well we'll see in the גמרא. gemara Let's take a look.
איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. So now we're going to try to figure
out what his reason is. טעמא דרבי יוסי משום דקסבר עובר במי
זרה זר הוא. Ta'ama d'Rabbi Yose mishum d'kasavar ubar b'mei zara zar
hu.
Maybe, and this is going to point to why, what רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose might really have been holding. Maybe the reason is not
that the עובר ubar has a portion of the slaves and the
slaves can't eat yet because he's not born. They can't eat through
him. Maybe the reason is that until he's born he's not yet
a כהן. kohen. So he has a portion of the slaves, but
the reason they can't eat by virtue of him is not that
you have to be alive and entitled to eat and therefore the
slaves can eat because you can eat. The reason they can't eat
is because he's a non-כהן kohen who owns them. עובר ירך אמו.
Ubar
yerech imo.
Right, yeah, exactly. So and while he's still in his mother and
before he gets his independent identity, and since his mother is a
non-כהן, kohen, he's a non-כהן. kohen. And therefore if he's a part
owner, they can't eat because part of them is owned by a
non-כהן. kohen. Okay, is that why? או דילמא ילוד מאכיל שאין ילוד
אינו מאכיל. O dilma yalud machil she'ein yalud eino machil. It has
nothing to do with him not being a כהן. kohen. He's a
כהן. kohen. But nevertheless, the principle is that slaves can only eat
by virtue of somebody who's born, not by virtue of somebody who's
unborn. So the obvious נפקא מינה nafka mina of those two cases
is: what if his mother is a בת כהן? bat kohen? Right,
that's the difference. Is it all because his mother's a ישראלית Yisraelit
and that makes him a זר, zar, or is it because he's
unborn? So that exactly seems to be what might be going on
in the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look. למאי נפקא מינה לעובר
במי כהנת מאי. L'mai nafka mina l'ubar b'mei kohenet mai. If his
mother's a כהנת, kohenet, a בת כהן, bat kohen, what's the story?
אמר רבה היינו טעמא דרבי יוסי דקסבר עובר במי זרה זר הוא.
Amar Rabbah hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Yose d'kasavar ubar b'mei zara zar hu.
Yeah, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose thinks it's because his mother's a non-כהן
kohen and therefore the עובר ubar is a זר. zar. רב יוסף
אמר ילוד מאכיל שאין ילוד אינו מאכיל.
Rav Yosef amar yalud machil
she'ein yalud eino machil. No, it's because he's unborn. It's not because
his mother's a non-כהן. kohen. So מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'm sorry, שאין ילוד
אינו מאכיל מיתיבי. she'ein yalud eino machil meitivei. Ask this. אמרו לו
לרבי יוסי מאחר שהערת לנו על בת ישראל לכהן, Amru lo l'Rabbi
Yose me'achar she'he'arta lanu al bat Yisrael le'kohen, once you told us
this is true if his mother is a בת ישראל, bat Yisrael,
בת כהן לכהן מהו? bat kohen le'kohen mahu? There's a ברייתא Braita
that elaborates on the משנה. Mishnah. What would you say the הלכה
halacha? is if his mother was a בת כהן? bat kohen? אמר
להם זו שמעתי וזו לא שמעתי. Amar lahem zo shamati v'zo lo
shamati. He said to them, this I heard and this I didn't
hear. No,
I have a tradition about when the mother's a ישראלית
Yisraelit that the slaves can't eat. When the mother's a בת כהן,
bat kohen, that I don't know. Which presumably that I don't have
a tradition, which presumably means that they could eat. So what would
be the reason for the difference? אי אמרת בשלמא עובר במי זרה
זר הוא היינו דקאמר להו זו שמעתי וזו לא שמעתי. Ei amrat
bishlama ubar b'mei zara zar hu hainu d'ka'amar lehu zo shamati v'zo
lo shamati. If it's for the reason that it's because he's a
זר, zar, so we understand why he only says this when his
mother's a ישראלית. Yisraelit. That's exactly the reason. אלא אי אמרת ילוד
מאכיל שאין ילוד אינו מאכיל מאי זו שמעתי וזו לא שמעתי. Ela
ei amrat yalud machil she'ein yalud eino machil mai zo shamati v'zo
lo shamati. Why would he not say, well of course you're right,
it is the same הלכה? halacha היא היא, Hi hi, it's the
exact same issue if it's about being born or unborn. תא שמע.
Ta shma. Okay, that's a good question we don't know. Which basically
means that the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose never out and out said
it's a different הלכה halacha. if the mother's a כהנת. kohenet. Clearly
the Rabbis said, based on your logic it should be the same
הלכה. So the Rabbis clearly understood רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that it's
about שאין ילוד אינו מאכיל, she'ein yalud eino machil, that as long
as you're not born your slaves can't eat on your behalf. Did
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose himself agree that that was the reason and
just didn't sort of draw the obvious the necessary conclusion, or was
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose really of a different position that it was
because his mother was a ישראלית Yisraelit and therefore the fetus was
considered a זר? zar? So we don't exactly know how to get
to the bottom of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, but it's clear that
that is the issue going on below the surface. Okay. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל זו דברי רבי יוסי. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
zo divrei Rabbi Yose. This is the position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval Chachamim omrim, but the sages say, because
this is the point in the משנה Mishnah it's not clear the
sages just disagree, they just want to say the logical conclusion of
what you said is that it applies even if the mother's a
כהן. kohen. But now we're going to have a real disagreement. This
is the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, but the sages say
יש לבנים
אוכלים משום בנים.
yesh l'banim ochlim
mishum banim. If there are already children, here is the mother who
is
pregnant. Are there other children or not to this כהן? kohen? If
there are other children they can eat by virtue of the other
children. The presence of a עובר, ubar, of an unborn fetus, doesn't
make it worse. אוכלים משום בנים. Ochlim mishum banim. אין לו בנים,
Ein lo banim, let's say there are no children, אוכלים משום אחים.
ochlim mishum achim.
Then who before a fetus is born the sages would be saying
not only like there are two assumptions of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
Number one is an unborn fetus already takes title of his inheritance,
you understand that that's assumption number one. And assumption number two is
That the slave can't eat by virtue of him because he's unborn.
So the חכמים chachamim here disagree with assumption number one. He doesn't
take assumption a title of his inheritance, so he's completely out of
the picture. So if there are brothers, they eat by virtue of
the brothers. I mean if there are sons, they eat by virtue
of the sons. If there are no sons, it's not like, well,
the עובר uber is now the heir. Right, remember, whether a boy
or a girl, if there's no other children, once this fetus is
born, he will be the heir. But says the חכמים chachamim until
he's born, we consider the brothers now the other relatives, the heirs.
Right, they basically say until this fetus is born, he is not
considered, he has no title to the estate.
Well, that's an interesting question, can they go ahead and waste the
money knowing that this guy will be born? I don't know the
answer to that, but their basic point is they, before you even
get to assumption two, can an unborn fetus have, you know, somebody
eat on his behalf? They say we disagree with assumption number one.
Before he's born, he has no title to the estate. Okay, and
therefore the slaves eat based on whoever is, whoever does have a
title for the time being. So let's...
Doesn't the woman actually own that property?
No, why does she own the property? What, the slaves? Yeah,
so let's assume, that's a good question, let's assume, you know, we'll
later be talking about, let's assume we're talking about נכסי צאן ברזל
nichsei tzon barzel before she retrieves them. Okay, or let's say we're
just talking about the husband's slaves that he has independently of her.
Those would be the ones she inherited. I know, I know, and
the משנה mishna was confusing because it said עבדיה, avadeha, so it
is a little confusing about that, but let's try to bracket that,
okay. So וחכמים אומרים יש לו בנים אוכלין משום בנים, אין לו
בנים אוכלין משום אחים, אין לו אחים אוכלין משום משפחה כולה. ve-chachamim
omrim yesh lo banim ochlin mishum banim ein lo banim ochlin mishum
achim ein lo achim ochlin mishum mishpacha kula.
Meaning there's somebody around that's related to this כהן kohen that's alive.
Okay, that person is the heir until the fetus is born and
for that, because of that person, the slave, the slaves can eat
תרומה, terumah, okay? Is that clear? So they basically reject the first
principle and they say until this עובר uber fetus is born, he's
not even in the picture.
Right. Okay. So that's the חכמים chachamim disagree, that's disagreeing with principle
number one. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says, okay,
so, זו ולא סבירא ליה. zu velo sevira leh. Now when שמואל
Shmuel says,
this is the words of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it sounds like
he's saying like, okay, that's יוסי's Yose's position but we don't hold
of it because there's this other position of the sages that completely
rejects it. So the גמרא gemara says, is that really true that
שמואל Shmuel doesn't hold of רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? זו ולא סבירא
ליה? zu velo sevira leh? והאמר ליה שמואל לרב חנא בגדתנא. ve-ha-amar
leh Shmuel le-Rav Chana Bagdatna. Now
what does בגדתנא Bagdatna mean? So if you look at רש"י Rashi
it's like two lines below the ב"ח, bach, רש"י Rashi says בגדתנא,
Bagdatna, first he says בעל אגדה, baal agada, or so he was
a, you know, he was somebody who liked sort of teaching אגדתא,
agadata, לשון אחר שם מקום שבבבל ששמו בגדת. lashon acher shem makom
she-be-Bavel she-shemo Bagdat. So anyway, which is probably the simpler פשט. pshat.
Okay, so שמואל Shmuel said to רב חנא... to
where were we? So is it really true that שמואל Shmuel rejects
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and says that the fetus has no rights
before he's born, no rights in the estate? והאמר ליה שמואל לרב
חנא בגדתנא פוק אייתי לי בי עשרה ואימא לכו באנפייהו, ve-ha-amar leh
Shmuel le-Rav Chana Bagdatna puk aytei li bei asara ve-eima lacho be-anpaihu,
I will tell you in their presence המזכה לעובר קנה ha-mezakeh le-uber
kanah that if somebody transfers title to a fetus, the fetus takes
possession. So get me ten people, I want to make a public
declaration. So you see שמואל Shmuel feels that you can transfer title
to a fetus. If you can transfer title to a fetus, presumably
a fetus also inherits while he is still a fetus. So how
do you do, you know, whatever, דעת אחרת מקנה אותו, daat acheret
maknah oto, you can be זוכה zocheh for somebody. Okay, so therefore,
so why is שמואל Shmuel saying, oh, this is what רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose holds? It sounds like you don't agree. But you certainly
agree to principle number one. You agree that a fetus is entitled
to a portion of the estate. So what do you mean, oh,
this is what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said? So the גמרא Gemara
says fine, אלא זו וסבירא ליה. ela zu ve-sevira leh. זו zu
doesn't mean he's dismissing it. This is what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says and this is how we hold. You should be aware this,
the חכמים chachamim that disagree, חכמים chachamim say the fetus isn't, doesn't
get a portion of the estate. I happen to agree with רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose and I say that a fetus does get a
portion of the estate. Okay, that was only by the way only
assumption number one of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So מאי קמ"ל דפליגי
עליה דרבנן דרבי יוסי mai ka mashma lan de-peligi alei derabbanan de-Rabbi
Yose and he's just telling you, look, I'm not saying we don't
rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, but you should be aware that
there is another opinion out there. There's a rabbis that disagree and
say the fetus doesn't have a portion.
Okay. ומי פליגי? umi paligi? Do the rabbis really argue? So the
word מתיב metiv is taken out, it says והאמר רבי זכאי זו
עדות העיד רבי יוסי מפי שמעיה ואבטליון. ve-ha-amar Rabbi Zakai zu edut
he-id Rabbi Yose mi-pi Shemaya ve-Avtalyon. This testimony that because of the
fetus, the slaves don't eat, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose gave in the
presence of שמעיה ואבטליון Shemaya ve-Avtalyon והודו לו, ve-hodu lo, and they
conceded to him. So if he testified to them and they agreed
to him, it sounds like there's a consensus opinion that he's right.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב אשי מי קתני וקבלו? amar
Rav Ashi mi katani ve-kibbelu? It doesn't say they accepted the position.
והודו לו קתני. ve-hodu lo katani. It says that they agreed. So
what's the difference between agreed and accepted? דמסתבר טעמיה. de-mistabar tameh. They
said, yeah, that actually makes a lot of sense. Okay, but it
doesn't mean they actually chose to פסק pasken like it. All right,
so now we have said that it's interesting, right? In the משנה,
Mishnah, you just have the חכמים Chachamim asking the rhetorical question. You
don't have it clear that anybody disagrees. The גמרא does present the
position of the חכמים Chachamim that disagree and disagree with assumption number
one, say the fetus has no portion in the estate until he's
born, but that even שמואל who presents that position of the חכמים
Chachamim himself himself sides with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and says the
fetus does have a position a portion in the estate. Yes.
Two chronologically, שמעיה Shemaya and אבטליון Avtalyon were generations before רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yossi.
Yeah, I was trying to figure that out too.
And בגדד Baghdad was founded in the 8th century by the Arabs.
Okay, so then בגדד Baghdad must be Baga-data, so thank you for
that. Okay.
All right, that's good to know. The רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi I
was wondering also in terms of the שמעיה Shemaya and אבטליון. Avtalyon.
I don't know, maybe there's a different רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
You said he testified in front of... before, right?
You said he testified? No, he testified in the presence... Oh, hey,
oh, you're right. I mistranslated it. Thank you. I, I, thank you,
thank you, I completely mistranslated it. He didn't testify in front of
שמעיה Shemaya and אבטליון. Avtalyon. He testified it in the name of
שמעיה Shemaya and אבטליון. Avtalyon. Thank you, Michael, I, I, mistranslated it.
That was a good catch. Okay, so he gave this teaching over
in the name of שמעיה Shemaya and אבטליון Avtalyon and they, I
guess the sages, admit conceded to him, or they said that it
was made a lot of sense, but they didn't decide to פסקן
pasken like it. Right, right, he it was a tradition in their
name. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. הניח בנים, Hinniach banim, אלו ואלו
אוכלין. elu vaelu ochlin.
Let's say she leaves over, he, what,
she's
not pregnant, okay, so,
well, right, we're not up to her being pregnant, right. So now
we're going to give all the scenarios. כהן Kohen dies, and there
are sons. Okay, and there are no, forget anybody being pregnant. אלו
ואלו, elu vaelu, these and they, meaning whether it's the נכסי מלוג,
nichsei melog, whether it's the נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, they
can eat. Why? The נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel can eat
because they're owned by, until she collects them, they're owned by the
sons. They're part of the estate. The נכסי מלוג nichsei melog can
eat, who owns the נכסי מלוג? nichsei melog? She does. Why can
they eat? Because if there are sons left from the marriage, she
can still eat, right? Once there are sons, even after he dies,
if there are children that are still left that, you know, have
resulted from the marriage, that are alive, she eats on their behalf.
She eats, you know, through them. So if there are children, both
his slaves eat and her slaves eat because everybody is eating by
account of the children. Okay. אלו ואלו אוכלין. elu vaelu ochlin. הניח
מעוברת, Hinniach muberet, let's say she, he left her pregnant. So, אלו
ואלו אין אוכלין. elu vaelu ein ochlin. That's the teaching of the
משנה. Mishnah. She can't eat until the child is born, she doesn't
eat on behalf of the children, and therefore her slaves don't eat.
And his slaves don't eat because this עובר ubar creates so this
difficulty that he's a partial owner but he can't eat they can't
eat on his account. אלו ואלו אין אוכלין. elu vaelu ein ochlin.
That's like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. הניח,
now, now we get in a mixed case. הניח בנים והניח מעוברת.
There are sons around and she's pregnant.
So, עבדי מלוג אוכלין avdei melog ochlin כדרך שהיא אוכלת. kederech shehi
ochelet. So because there are children around, she's entitled to eat, right?
The fact that there's any child that's around and born entitles her
to eat and therefore her slaves can eat.
עבדי צאן ברזל לא יאכלו מפני חלקו של עובר. avdei tzon barzel
lo yochlu mipnei chelko shel ubar. But the fetus's part ownership in
his estate prevents his slaves from eating. שהעובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל. shehaubar
poseil veeino maachil. The עובר ubar invalidates, you know, the one that
he's a partial owner in, so even though there are other children
who are also heirs, his partial ownership creates a problem and it
can't cause his mother to eat or his mother's slave to eat,
but the other sons, the born children do allow his mother to
eat. דברי רבי יוסי. divrei Rabbi Yossi. That's what רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi says. So that was just a nice playing out of the
משנה. Mishnah. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yishmael bRabbi Yossi omer,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael his son says, משום אביו mishum aviv in
the name of his father, so הבת מאכילה הבן אינו מאכיל. habat
maachelet haben eino maachil. The daughter can have the mother eat, but
not the son. Not clear all what that means, the גמרא will
unpack that. Okay. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai
omer, רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai says, זכרים יאכלו
כולן נקבות לא יאכלו. zecharim yochlu kulan nekeivot lo yochlu. שמא ימצא
עובר ז, shema yimtza ubar za, you know, I think we have
to end here. Okay, we will continue this משנה Mishnah and see
the range of positions of these scenarios tomorrow as we